<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-12-20T04:05:20+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Integrated Modelling and Testing Architecture for ROS Nodes</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2023/roscon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Integrated Modelling and Testing Architecture for ROS Nodes"/><published>2023-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2023/roscon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2023/roscon/"><![CDATA[<p>Often in robotics research, software is co-developed in multiple programming languages: a scripted language like Matlab for algorithm development, and a compiled language like C++ for deployed code. While scripted languages can initially improve development speed, the need to transfer to a compiled language for performance reasons can lead to costly debugging which increases with system complexity over time. In a new project, EKF-CAL, ROS node code is integrated with a multi-fidelity simulation framework. This framework is presented alongside techniques used to improve the long-term quality of deployed ROS code using unit and Monte Carlo testing.</p> <p>This presentation was given as <a href="https://roscon.ros.org/2023/">RosCon 2023</a> with both <a href="https://roscon.ros.org/talks/An_Integrated_Modelling_and_Testing_Architecture_for_ROS_Nodes.pdf">slides</a> and a <a href="https://vimeo.com/879000742/0d9939e399">video</a> recording available online.</p> <p><a href="https://vimeo.com/879000742/0d9939e399"> <img src="/assets/img/roscon.jpeg" alt="UWB Ranging" class="center" style="width:50%"/> </a></p>]]></content><author><name>Jacob Hartzer</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Often in robotics research, software is co-developed in multiple programming languages: a scripted language like Matlab for algorithm development, and a compiled language like C++ for deployed code. While scripted languages can initially improve development speed, the need to transfer to a compiled language for performance reasons can lead to costly debugging which increases with system complexity over time. In a new project, EKF-CAL, ROS node code is integrated with a multi-fidelity simulation framework. This framework is presented alongside techniques used to improve the long-term quality of deployed ROS code using unit and Monte Carlo testing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Online Multi-Camera and IMU Calibration</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2022/multi-cam-IMU-calibration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Multi-Camera and IMU Calibration"/><published>2022-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2022/multi-cam-IMU-calibration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2022/multi-cam-IMU-calibration/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/multi_cam_imu/setup.png" alt="UWB Ranging" style="float:right;width:30%"/></p> <p>This research focuses on the implementation of an online multi-camera IMU calibration filter that is based on the work of <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/IROS.2007.4399342">Mirzaei and Roumeliotis</a>. This work expands on what has been previously done by incorporating the fiducial marker detectors provided by <a href="https://opencv.org/">OpenCV</a> and manipulating the update equations to utilize the quaternion measurement provided by these detectors.</p> <p>The main challenge was in developing the Jacobians for the quaternion measurement, such that the updates would be stable even with large body rotations. To overcome this challenge, the derivations and work by Joan Sola which can be found on <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1711.02508">ArXiv</a> were used extensively.</p> <p>Additionally, work was performed on monitoring the calibration for shifts in extrinsic parameters, such as would occur if a sensor is bumped in the middle of use. Through the use of a sliding window T-test, online monitoring of calibration extrinsic parameters was implemented.</p> <h2 id="experimentation">Experimentation</h2> <p><img src="/assets/img/multi_cam_imu/8020.png" alt="UWB Ranging" style="float:right;width:30%"/></p> <p>Testing was performed using a bar of 8020 with multiple camera mounts and a IMU/INS. This allowed for multiple sensor configurations and rapid recalibration testing with different sensor configurations. The specific sensors tested were:</p> <ul> <li>IMUs: <ul> <li>Vectornav VN300 </li> <li>Vectornav VN100 </li> <li>Wheeltec FDISystems N100N</li> <li>Pixhawk PX4</li> <li>WitMotion WT901C485</li> </ul> </li> <li>Cameras:  <ul> <li>Flir Blackfly BFLY-PGE-20E4C-CS </li> <li>Basler Ace acA1920-40uc </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h2 id="code">Code</h2> <p>The code has been open-sourced and is available on <a href="https://github.com/unmannedlab/multi-cam-imu-cal">Github</a>. Feel free to fork, update and create pull requests where you see fit, so long as you adhere to the GPL3 license.</p> <h2 id="citation">Citation:</h2> <p>This content was presented at SSRR 2022 with slides available <a href="/assets/pdf/2021-09-ITSC.pdf">here</a>. The published article is available on <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.13821">arXiv</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/SSRR56537.2022.10018692">IEEE</a>.</p> <div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">2022_Multi_Cal</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span>    <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Hartzer, Jacob and Saripalli, Srikanth}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2022 IEEE International Symposium on Safety, Security, and Rescue Robotics (SSRR)}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Online Multi Camera-IMU Calibration}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span>      <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2022}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">pages</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{360-365}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">doi</span>       <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{10.1109/SSRR56537.2022.10018692}</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name>Jacob Hartzer</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In Offense of the Electoral College</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/electoral-college/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In Offense of the Electoral College"/><published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/electoral-college</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/electoral-college/"><![CDATA[<p>The Electoral College, in its current form, is undemocratic, effectively disenfranchises millions of Americans, discourages participation in government, and has drifted away from what the framers of our Constitution intended. A system that allows for a candidate to receive <a href="https://www.npr.org/2016/11/02/500112248/how-to-win-the-presidency-with-27-percent-of-the-popular-vote">less than 25% of the popular vote</a>, and still become president of the United States has fatal flaws and has no place in a modern democracy. Though we have yet to see something that egregious in an election, our refusal to modernize despite demographic trends will only exacerbate the disparities where twice in the past 20 years the president was not chosen by a majority of the American people.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/EC.png" alt="English Unit Countries" style="float:right;width:400px"/></p> <h1 id="the-framers-intentions">The Framers’ Intentions</h1> <p>Since the national popular vote was first recorded in 1824, there have been five presidential elections where the <a href="https://ballotpedia.org/Splits_between_the_Electoral_College_and_popular_vote">winner lost the popular vote</a>, the most recent being Donald Trump who, in 2016, lost the popular vote by 2.9M. In fact, the year that votes were first recorded, John Quincy Adams won neither the Electoral College nor the popular vote, losing by 15 EC votes and 44K in the popular vote. This begs the question, why is the president elected by the Electoral College instead of through direct democracy, like both the US House and Senate, State Houses and Senates, and State governors.</p> <p>In a Heritage Foundation paper, Hans von Spakovsky noted “In creating the basic architecture of the American government, the Founders struggled to satisfy each state’s demand for greater representation while attempting to balance popular sovereignty against the risk posed to the minority from majoritarian rule.” Though debated thoroughly, the Electoral College was created as a compromise between a president chosen by congress and a president chosen by a popular vote. This balanced empowering individuals through democracy and creating an intermediate body to protect against previous failings of unrestrained democracy. This system is similar to our Republic of congress, whereby elected individuals make policy decisions. However, the Electoral College creates a second degree of separation between policy decisions of the president and the electorate.</p> <p>The framers were aware of the issue of so-called mob rule, since they themselves were elites. They were scared of the prospect of every white man being able to vote directly on policy, which they feared could lead to a form of tyranny of the majority. As such, the United States is a Democratic Republic, whereby representatives elected directly by the people, would make decisions on behalf of the electorate. If it is sufficient for senators and representatives to be chosen by direct democracy by those they represent, why not also the president? There is still an elected office between the electorate and the decisions made. The United States being a democratic republic protects us from the so-called mob rule, not the Electoral College. If the intention was to subvert the popular vote when the people select demagogues, criminals, or the inept, the Electoral College cannot be a guaranteed solution. States are allowed to appoint their electors as they choose. If every state were to outlaw faithless electors, as is their lawful ability to, then there would be no intermediary between the Electoral College and the will of the people, thereby rendering this possible intention worthless.</p> <p>Additionally, it would be silly to say that the framers of the Constitution had the advantage of small rural states in mind when the Constitution was written. In 1800, 94% of Americans lived in rural areas. The urban majority shift to cities didn’t occur until 1920. I don’t believe, therefore, that the framers expected this shift and wanted to protect small states from the tyranny of larger, more populated states. Instead it was originally a balance of direct democracy, a republic, and an aristocracy. It was created to prevent regional politicians from ignoring other parts of the United States and simply focusing on a specific area. It was a compromise to give power to smaller slave holding states that wanted to see an advantage not only in representation through the racist <a href="https://www.history.com/news/electoral-college-founding-fathers-constitutional-convention">three fifths compromise</a>, but also in the presidential election.</p> <p>Lastly, it is very unlikely the founding fathers knew what the world would be like today. Even if they did, I would not exactly trust the opinions of 39 <a href="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2013/08/how-old-were-the-founding-fathers-the-leaders-of-the-american-revolution-were-younger-than-we-imagine.html">young</a>, white, land holding men from 1787 to decide what is best for the United States in 2020. They did not agree that black Americans could be considered people, or that women have an equal place in the world. They knew nothing of the technologies that would propel our country to prominence after the two world wars they were entirely ignorant of. Yes the founding fathers were able to create the longest lasting democracy in history, but that doesn’t mean their ideas were perfect. There is a reason why there have been 27 amendments to the Constitution, with the latest change being proposed on March 23, 1971! We are in an evolving democracy, and it is ignorant of us to assume that those 39 while men in 1787 knew what would be best for our country now in 2020. We have the power to improve our country, and currently, the Electoral College remains an artifact that stands in the way of millions of Americans participating in choosing their president.</p> <h1 id="issues-with-the-electoral-college">Issues with the Electoral College</h1> <p>The Electoral College does not ensure that small states are given additional consideration in presidential campaigning. I cannot recall, in my relatively short life, a time when a presidential candidate seriously campaigned in Texas. Why not? Because it is not a swing state. Due to the ineffectiveness of the Electoral College, a majority of resources in presidential campaigns are focused among the states that have possibilities of swinging either way. This guarantees that the presidential candidates have to consider minority issues of these states far more than those from a solidly Republican or Democratic state. In 2008, there were 18 states that no presidential candidate visited within 2 months of the election with two-thirds of visits and funding going to just <a href="https://www.nationalpopularvote.com/campaign-events-2016">six states</a> and 94% going to just twelve. That doesn’t sound like small states being heard or cared about, nor does it guarantee their concerns are to be heard. As long as small states are solidly Republican or Democratic, no mind will be paid to them by either party. Additionally, because of the dispersion of US cities, there is no way to just visit a few large population centers and win over a majority of the people, as is a common rebuttal. The top 100 cities in the US make up less than 20% of the total population. Therefore, even without the Electoral College, it is necessary for candidates to consider the needs of larger groups of populations than just a few select cities.</p> <p>Being in a more populated state, we Texans should be angry by our poor representation. A Texan vote for president counts only 28.4% of a Wyoming vote for president. Why is it that those in Wyoming should have 3.5 times the voting power of us in Texas? This problem will only continue to worsen. By 2040, it is projected that the United States will have 380M people. As this growth will be concentrated in urban areas, states that are currently underrepresented will likely grow less represented with time. As time goes on, our votes in Texas count less and less, and the Electoral College, in its current state, has no remedy for this problem.</p> <p>Most of all, the reason why I want to see the Electoral College abolished is because I want my vote for president to count. As a progressive in a solidly red state and district, my vote for president does nothing. As long as I am the guaranteed minority party, there is no reason for me to vote for President. This is a deeply troubling and discouraging reality to come to grips with. A liberal in Texas or a conservative in California have no way, with the Electoral College, to influence the outcome of the presidential election. That alone should be disqualifying for the institution. Why should people participate in our government, when they are essentially barred from impacting an election based on where they live? Even more ridiculous is the impact it has on the winning side as well. Why should Democrats in California or Republicans in Texas actually show up to vote for president when it is almost guaranteed that their state will go their way? The Electoral College encourages complacency in our citizens, and <a href="https://www.cnn.com/election/2016/results/president">nullifies the votes of 63M people</a> who voted for the losing side in their state. I think those votes matter, and I think it’s important for our electoral systems to reflect those values. Unfortunately, with the outdated system of the Electoral College, we will only see a continual worsening of our democracy and render useless the voices of millions of Americans in the selection of our president.</p> <h1 id="subverting-the-electoral-college">Subverting the Electoral College</h1> <p>Currently, there is an effort to effectively remove the Electoral College without requiring a constitutional amendment. As outlined in the Constitution, States have wide discretion in the appointment of electors. Therefore, States may require, legally, that electors vote for the winner of the popular vote within their state, or even the popular vote of the entire country. The National Popular Vote Interstate Compact (NPVIC) is an agreement between States to appoint electors for whatever candidate wins the popular vote. The catch is the agreement does not become binding until enough States join the agreement as to guarantee 270 Electoral College votes. Currently, the agreement has 196 electoral votes. Once it reaches the threshold, then it will not matter how the remaining states appoint electors, as it would be guaranteed for the president to be selected by the national popular vote, a direct democratic process.</p> <p>Possible issues with this agreement is the Compact Clause of the Constitution, whereby “No State shall, without the Consent of Congress … enter into any Agreement or Compact with another State.” The constitutionality of the NPVIC likely will not be decided until it determines the outcome of an election, which could be many years down the line. With each state added, the next becomes more reluctant. So, what could we do to fix the Electoral College today?</p> <h1 id="fixing-the-electoral-college">Fixing the Electoral College</h1> <p>If the framers did think the current Electoral College was the proper way to select the president, the size of congress would have been fixed. In order to address the population disparities we are currently living through, the US used to add more members to congress to protect against such unequal treatment of citizens between various states. The so-called “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wyoming_Rule">Wyoming Rule</a>” used to ensure that representation in the House was apportioned by the smallest population state, where the size of the house was increased to account for ratios of the smallest state to the largest state. Because this rule was given up due to a <a href="https://history.house.gov/Historical-Highlights/1901-1950/The-Permanent-Apportionment-Act-of-1929/">resolution in 1929</a> after a controversy during the 1920 census, the number of seats in the house has remained fixed at the 1910 census number, 435 seats. There is no reason why we cannot double the number of seats in the house to more evenly apportion representation. It is possible that we simply increase the size of the House to 547 seats to follow the Wyoming Rule. This would not go against what the framers intended, nor would it be any different from how our country determined the size of the house since before 1929. If you believe in the Electoral College and the intention of the framers of the Constitution, then the Wyoming rule should be <a href="https://www.dailykos.com/stories/2018/7/5/1778149/-Implementing-the-Wyoming-Rule">reimplemented</a> such that the disparity of congressional representation between states can be remedied. This would reduce the likelihood of presidents being elected without winning the popular vote and would not require an amendment to the Constitution (though some renovations might need to be made to expand the white house).</p> <h1 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h1> <p>There have been multiple constitutional amendments proposed to abolish the Electoral College. The closest we came to removing it was with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electoral_College_abolition_amendment">Bayh–Celler amendment of 1969</a>. The amendment passed the house and even began debate in the senate, but was quickly filibustered by small states wanting to retain their power. Unable to receive the two-thirds majority needed to end the filibuster, the amendment failed. It is fitting that the last time we got close to removing this undemocratic institution, our efforts were stopped by a minority acting in their own best interest. The Electoral College is a holdover from undemocratic and racist ideals that the people must be further removed from the president than any other elected official. The inability of the Electoral College to grow or evolve in the past 100 years has exacerbated its flaws, and we are at a breaking point. When so many today are challenging the foundations of our democracy, we should not keep a system that causes people to lose faith in the election process. I want my vote to count. As do I want yours. Fix the Electoral College or get rid of it.</p> <h1 id="additional-information">Additional Information</h1> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.cnsnews.com/commentary/jarrett-stepman/why-america-uses-electoral-college-not-popular-vote-presidential-election">Why America Uses Electoral College, Not Popular Vote for Presidential Election</a></li> <li><a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/155134/case-popular-vote">The Case Against the Popular Vote</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.cgpgrey.com/the-electoral-college/">GCP Grey: The Electoral College</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Electoral College, in its current form, is undemocratic, effectively disenfranchises millions of Americans, discourages participation in government, and has drifted away from what the framers of our Constitution intended. A system that allows for a candidate to receive less than 25% of the popular vote, and still become president of the United States has fatal flaws and has no place in a modern democracy. Though we have yet to see something that egregious in an election, our refusal to modernize despite demographic trends will only exacerbate the disparities where twice in the past 20 years the president was not chosen by a majority of the American people.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Cost of Outdated English Units</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/metric-system/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cost of Outdated English Units"/><published>2020-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/metric-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/metric-system/"><![CDATA[<p>Burma, Liberia, and the US. Three countries that you don’t normally hear grouped together in the same sentence. None share a continent, many would have trouble locating all three on a map. Yet there they are. The reason I have gathered these countries together in the opening sentence of this essay is that these are the only three remaining countries on the Earth that have not adopted the International System of Units, better known as the metric system.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/metric.png" alt="English Unit Countries" style="float:right;width:400px"/></p> <h1 id="ease-of-use">Ease of Use</h1> <p>But wait, fractions are so much easier in a base twelve system! This breaks down as soon as you want a third of an inch, instead of a third of a foot. Sure base twelve is great for dividing, but why is there base two system in there, too? Where are the benefits of a base twelve system in the fractions of an inch?</p> <p>And of course it makes perfect sense to measure distance in miles, the most intuitive unit of distance. Why what is a mile you ask, 5280 feet! It’s easy to remember, you see. A mile is eight furlongs, the length of a furrow that a team of oxen could plow in a single day, which is 660 feet. And the English Parliament decided in 1592 that was close enough to the 5000 roman feet that originally defined a mile. So if you ever forget, just remember that it is a close approximation of 1000 paces of the average roman man, rounded to eight times the length that a team of oxen can plow in a day.</p> <p>The point is, decimal systems are pretty well engrained into Humans. We have ten digits. Our numbering system is base 10. The idea of a system of units that conforms to this intuition makes for a simpler and more efficient system of measurement.</p> <h1 id="think-of-the-poor-scientists-and-engineers">Think of the Poor Scientists and Engineers</h1> <p>And if those reasons aren’t enough, I can personally attest that being forced to occasionally work in customary units is terrible. I hate having to convert between slugs, oz-inches, pound-mass, and pound-force (those last two mean shockingly different things depending on what planet you are on). They are not intuitive, and they are bound to make any engineering student groan. Myself and many others would rather convert entire problems to SI units and back, instead of using the customary units thrust upon us by society.</p> <p>The difficulty in dealing with multiple systems of units has caused a number of failures over the years. The most famous, and likely most expensive, of these mishaps is when NASA lost a Mars orbiter due to a unit conversion error. This failure cost NASA $327M, which could have been resolved if the United States used the metric system.</p> <h1 id="costs-of-the-customary-system">Costs of the Customary System</h1> <p>There is a cost to the time it takes to convert units. This is both an issue for Americans dealing with themselves and when dealing with other countries. Converting millions of inches to miles takes time, and that time is needlessly wasted on an archaic system of measurement. Time is wasted every time a transaction occurs for materials, or plans are made between entities. All of these seconds add up, and the longer we go without switching, the more time and energy will be wasted. J. V. Collins estimated in 1915 that the US was losing $315M a year from a lack of conversion, counting for inflation this would come out to $8.1B lost annually in 2020.</p> <p>There is a cost to maintaining different standards for SI and customary units. Machinists need capabilities for two types of threads, which each have multiple thread specifications.</p> <p>To add to the frustration, we actually use SI units every day. Not even in the cheeky “seconds are SI units” way. By definition, every inch, milk, gallon, and pound that is ever measured, is actually measured in reference to the corresponding SI unit. Ever since the International Yard and Pound Agreement of July 1, 1959, customary units have been, by definition, calculated from a standard in the metric system. Where scientists have been able to define SI units in terms of physical phenomena and first principles, there don’t seem to be any that work in customary units to have done the same. So not only should we switch to the metric system, but it is actually foundational to the system we are already using.</p> <h1 id="sources">Sources:</h1> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.rd.com/article/why-5280-feet-in-mile/">History of Customary Mile</a></li> <li><a href="https://todayinsci.com/Events/Measurement/AMetricalTragedy.htm">A Metrical Tragedy</a></li> <li><a href="https://everydayastronaut.com/mars-climate-orbiter/">Metric mishap caused loss of NASA orbiter</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.edweek.org/ew/articles/1992/12/09/14phelps.h12.html">The Case for U.S. Metric Conversion Now</a></li> <li><a href="https://usma.org/laws-and-bills/metric-conversion-act-of-1975">The Metric Conversion Act of 1975</a></li> <li><a href="https://units.fandom.com/wiki/International_yard">International Yard Pound Agreement</a></li> <li><a href="https://usma.org/#information-about">U.S. Metric Association</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Burma, Liberia, and the US. Three countries that you don’t normally hear grouped together in the same sentence. None share a continent, many would have trouble locating all three on a map. Yet there they are. The reason I have gathered these countries together in the opening sentence of this essay is that these are the only three remaining countries on the Earth that have not adopted the International System of Units, better known as the metric system.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Collaborative Localization using Ultra-Wideband Ranging</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/UWB-Localization/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collaborative Localization using Ultra-Wideband Ranging"/><published>2020-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/UWB-Localization</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/UWB-Localization/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1> <p>There are numerous industries that are in the process of developing autonomous passenger vehicles. Such vehicles have the capacity to reduce risk and free time of riders. In the development of an autonomous vehicles, a key consideration is reliable localization in order to plan for and react to the environment. Typically,h igh position accuracy is achieved through the use of Global Navigation Satellite Systems (GNSS). The use of GNSS with an Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU) or odometry measurements can lead to an accurate positioning system. <img src="/assets/img/uwb/uwb_collab.png" alt="UWB Ranging" style="float:right;width:400px"/></p> <p>Reliable GNSS measurements are often not available. Because GNSS receivers must have line of sight with at least four satellites, environments that include obstructions pose significant challenges. Urban canyons, tunnels, or indoor environments degrade or fully obstruct GNSS signals, forcing the system to rely on dead reckoning. These measurements are subject to drift, and therefore cannot be trusted after continued interruption of GNSS. As such, it would be advantageous to the continued development of autonomous vehicles to use a exteroceptive sensor for navigation through environments where GNSS is typically denied.</p> <p>Ultra-Wideband (UWB) radio, utilizes low-energy pulse communication typically for short-range, high-bandwidth applications. By measuring time of flight across various frequencies, it is possible to measure distance between modules while overcoming multipath errors. This has allowed UWB modules to be applied towards localization and tracking problems. With the continued development of UWB technology and roll out in commercial products, it’s ability to aid in navigation should continue to be explored.</p> <p>By using UWB ranging, autonomous vehicles can generate ranging estimates to other independent vehicles. Just like measurements to landmarks, these measurements are not subject to drift when GNSS measurements are obscured, and can be made available in both indoor and outdoor environments. Known as collaborative localization, these measurements can leverage the growing number of intelligent vehicles on the road, and can increase the accessible area of autonomous vehicles.</p> <h1 id="background">Background</h1> <p>Ultra-Wideband, with it’s previously mentioned benefits, is a very promising technology for localization. There are many examples of using UWB ranging modules for high-accuracy indoor localization of ground or aerial systems. These systems typically measure with respect to fixed landmark anchors.</p> <p>There are also examples of using UWB modules for outdoor vehicular environments. Such a framework has the capacity to increase localization accuracy of existing systems, or provide accurate localization in environments where GNSS is not reliable, such as tunnels or urban canyons.</p> <p>Given a network of vehicles, it is possible to leverage relative measurements to provide better localization accuracy as a group, than as a collection of individuals, generally referred to as collaborative localization (CL). These methods are generally classified in two groups: centralized methods, and decentralized methods.</p> <h4 id="centralized-cl">Centralized CL</h4> <p>Centralized CL methods use a single or multiple fusion centers, to which every vehicle communicates measurement information. These state estimators are capable of producing optimal linearized state estimates and have been used in a number of applications with success. A major issue with centralized networks is sensitivity to failure. As the number of measurements made can increase on the order of O(n^2), centralized networks can meet constraints when large networks of nodes are implemented with complex measurements or update functions.</p> <h4 id="decentralized-cl">Decentralized CL</h4> <p>Decentralized CL (DCL) methods are defined by distributing the state estimation computation across every agent in the network. Unlike centralized methods, DCL methods are not susceptible to single point failures. These generic, recursive approximations of the centralized method can extend the framework to decrease convergence time or computational cost without loss of accuracy.</p> <h1 id="contributions">Contributions</h1> <p>This research seeks to expand upon previous work through the following contributions</p> <ul> <li>Expanded previous UWB EKF and DCL simulation environments through the incorporation of vehicle and sensor models and the framework for Monte Carlo simulations.</li> <li>Validated the zero-mean normally distributed error assumption for a UWB ranging module.</li> <li>Showed EKF localization improvements using real-time UWB measurements to landmarks in GNSS denied environments.</li> <li>Showed DCL accuracy improvements by utilizing real-time UWB relative ranging measurements.</li> </ul> <h1 id="decentralized-collaborative-localization">Decentralized Collaborative Localization</h1> <p>The decentralized collaborative localization algorithm is a form of a Kalman filter that approximates the centralized filter through distributed computation. The estimation of the entire state of a network is broken down into smaller filters where each vehicle has private controls and measurements that are used internally and relative measurements that require the sharing of state and covariance information.</p> <p>For a network of N vehicles, each vehicle initializes its own 6-DOF state and assumes zero cross-correlations between the vehicles until a relative measurement is made. As such, the number of vehicles does not need to be known.</p> <h4 id="initialization">Initialization</h4> <p>It is assumed that at the beginning of any network, the vehicles positions are uncorrelated. Therefore, the network state can be initialized with the initial beliefs of each vehicle and the cross correlation is set as a zero matrix.</p> <p>When the vehicles come into sensing range, generally the cross correlation is no longer equal to zero and therefore the cross-correlation term can be decomposed to allow each vehicle to maintain estimates of cross correlation terms that can be combined at the next relative measurement. The decomposition sets the cross-correlation of the sensing vehicle equal to the true cross-correlation and the sensed vehicle estimate equal to the identity matrix.</p> <h4 id="control">Control</h4> <p>It is assumed that the vehicles follow the motion model <em>g(U)</em> where control input U is an IMU measurement. The prediction step for a vehicle is given by the standard EKF equations.</p> <h4 id="private-update">Private Update</h4> <p>It is assumed that the private update measurements are functions of the state of a single vehicle with a Gaussian error disturbance <em>h(x)</em>. These updates come from GNSS positioning and UWB landmark ranging measurements.</p> <h4 id="relative-update">Relative Update</h4> <p>It is assumed that the relative update measurement to be a function of the state of two vehicles with a Gaussian error disturbance. These updates come from vehicle-to-vehicle relative UWB ranging measurements. The cross-correlation estimates are combined to be used in the best state estimate of the approximated system.</p> <h1 id="simulation">Simulation</h1> <p><img src="/assets/img/uwb/sc.png" alt="UWB Ranging" style="float:right;width:400px"/></p> <p>In order to simulate various collaborative localization algorithms, a simulation framework that would be flexible in number of cars and networking was created in MatLab: <a href="https://github.com/unmannedlab/collab_localization">collab_localization</a> repository. The simulation was designed to handle an indeterminate number of cars and configurations. Additionally, to facilitate the testing of collaborative localization, UWB tags can be treated as either fixed landmarks or mobile units on other vehicles.</p> <h4 id="sensing-models">Sensing Models</h4> <p>The UWB sensing model was implemented with Gaussian normal randomly distributed errors with a measured standard deviation of 0.31 meters.</p> <p>The GNSS sensing model takes a Circular Error Probable (CEP) error value and converts into a distance root mean square (DRMS), which is approximately 84.93\% of CEP. This DRMS value is input to a circularly symmetric Rayleigh distribution to perturb the measurement.</p> <h4 id="output">Output</h4> <p>The resulting output of this software package is a visual animation of the simulation, position error summaries for each vehicle, and the final state and covariance. When compiled in Monte Carlo simulations, these data can be used to evaluate filter performance improvements.</p> <h4 id="results">Results</h4> <p><img src="/assets/img/uwb/err_sc.png" alt="UWB Ranging" style="float:right;width:400px"/></p> <p>Using the simulation framework, it was possible to test a wide variety of vehicle environments and sensor configurations. These configurations included vehicles moving parallel to each other, vehicles moving perpendicular in street crossings, and moving in groups in tunnels without GNSS measurements. Additionally, UWB landmarks were added to each of these situations.</p> <p>Examples of the Monte Carlo simulations performed are shown. These figures show the crossing of two vehicles at an intersection using various estimation algorithms.</p> <p>The simulations showed that UWB measurements offered improvements to localization accuracy across all experiments. Using more vehicles improved accuracy, and using additional landmarks offered significant improvements. This was especially the case in situations where GNSS data was not available such as tunnels and urban canyons.</p> <h1 id="experimentation">Experimentation</h1> <p>The filter framework was tested in Bryan, Texas using the Unmanned Systems Lab autonomous trolley. The Decawave EVK1000 evaluation boards were mounted alongside a VectorNav VN-300 and ArduSimple RTK GNSS. The trolley itself includes PACMod, a by-wire kit prepared by Autonomous Stuff, which gives access to wheel odometry and steering data.</p> <p>Using tripods, a second set of UWB ranging modules were placed in various experimental setups to either represent road landmarks, or a second vehicle.</p> <p>As in the simulations, the addition of the two UWB sensors on the vehicle offered improvements to the localization accuracy of the vehicle in all scenarios. The improvement was even more pronounced when GNSS data to the VN-300 was denied. The quality of data coming from the VN-300 was underestimated, leading to much higher location accuracy than simulated. As such, the percent improvement from simply adding UWB measurements was lower than in the simulations, with the smallest percent improvement being 2.9% and the largest being 9.3%. However, removing the GNSS updates showed results much more in line with the simulation, with the addition of UWB measurements showing a 83.3% improvement in localization accuracy in a tunnel environment.</p> <h1 id="future-work">Future Work</h1> <p>Future work for this research includes</p> <ul> <li>Experiments with additional tags and multiple moving vehicles</li> <li>Explore transitional space between GPS and GPS-denied environments</li> <li>Compare the decentralized approximation to the centralized method</li> <li>Simulate the effects of delays in the system</li> </ul> <p>In the future, testing will include more in-person experiments with multiple moving vehicles and a greater number of UWB tags. This would allow for better evaluation of truly cooperative localization using of vehicles using UWB and will validate the algorithm used in simulation. This will also explore the use of real-time varying covariance estimations in the update equations.</p> <h1 id="citation">Citation</h1> <p>This content was presented at ITSC 2021 with slides available <a href="/assets/pdf/2021-09-ITSC.pdf">here</a>.</p> <div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">2021_Vehicular_Teamwork</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span>    <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Hartzer, Jacob and Saripalli, Srikanth}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2021 IEEE International Intelligent Transportation Systems Conference (ITSC)}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Vehicular Teamwork: Collaborative localization of Autonomous Vehicles}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span>      <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2021}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">pages</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{1077-1082}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">doi</span>       <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{10.1109/ITSC48978.2021.9564981}</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <h1 id="related-works">Related Works</h1> <ol> <li>L. Yao, Y. A. Wu, L. Yao, and Z. Z. Liao, “<strong>An integrated IMU and UWB sensor based indoor positioning system</strong>,” in <em>2017 International Conference on Indoor Positioning and Indoor Navigation (IPIN)</em>, pp. 1–8, 2017.</li> <li>L. Luft, T. Schubert, S. I. Roumeliotis, and W. Burgard, “<strong>Recursive decentralized localization for multi-robot systems with asynchronous pairwise communication</strong>,” <em>The International Journal of Robotics Research</em>, vol. 37, no. 10, pp. 1152–1167, 2018.</li> <li>S. I. Roumeliotis and G. A. Bekey, “Distributed multirobot localization,”IEEE Transactionson Robotics and Automation, vol. 18, no. 5, pp. 781–795, 2002</li> <li>S. Tanwar and G. Gao, “<strong>Decentralized collaborative localization with deep gps coupling for UAVs</strong>,” in <em>2018 IEEE/ION Position, Location and Navigation Symposium, PLANS 2018 - Proceedings</em>, (United States), pp. 767–774, June 2018.</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Localization"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction There are numerous industries that are in the process of developing autonomous passenger vehicles. Such vehicles have the capacity to reduce risk and free time of riders. In the development of an autonomous vehicles, a key consideration is reliable localization in order to plan for and react to the environment. Typically,h igh position accuracy is achieved through the use of Global Navigation Satellite Systems (GNSS). The use of GNSS with an Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU) or odometry measurements can lead to an accurate positioning system.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I built a Website using Jekyll</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/making-a-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I built a Website using Jekyll"/><published>2020-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/making-a-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/making-a-website/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/jekyll.png" alt="Jekyll" style="float:right;width:25%"/></p> <p>A mechanical engineer with a website, how peculiar you might say! I promise it’s easy and you can do the same. This is a static-site hosted on github pages that I can easily edit and push changes to using my home desktop. It is build using a Ruby Gem called <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">jekyll</a> which really was the catalyst for me to create this site. If something this good looking had to be created from scratch, I would still be stuck in mid-2000’s html land.</p> <h2 id="install-jekyll">Install Jekyll</h2> <p>I would recommend following the jekyll <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/">Quick Start Guide</a> for instructions on setting up a Ruby environment, bundler, and jekyll. This is a relatively painless process, and can be done on any OS.</p> <h2 id="create-your-site">Create your site</h2> <p>The way that I built this site and the way I recommend others to is to start with a template and then modify it to meet your own particular needs. There are sites that aggregate <a href="http://jekyllthemes.org/">jekyll themes</a> that can be used or purchased. I forked my site template from Dean Attali’s <a href="https://github.com/daattali/beautiful-jekyll#readme">beautiful-jekyll</a> which has really expanded my perspective of what is possible using a static site. Responsive design and consideration for phones were not things that I had originally anticipated when I started looking into the css, but I am glad that I had a foundation to modify and experiment with.</p> <h2 id="advanced-generation">Advanced Generation</h2> <p>Jekyll uses the <a href="https://shopify.github.io/liquid/">Liquid</a> template language to process templates. You can read jekyll’s documentation <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/liquid/">here</a>. The biggest takeaways, in my opinion, are the use of liquid variables to iterate through build pages, and define how certain pages are to be treated.</p> <h2 id="in-short">In Short</h2> <p>Jekyll makes build a static site extremely easy, and GitHub has removed the cost normally associated with hosting a site. There’s nothing to lose, so good luck and go try it!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Autonomous Cone Placement</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/auto-cones/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Autonomous Cone Placement"/><published>2020-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/auto-cones</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2020/auto-cones/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/ConeSetup.png" alt="cone" style="float:right;width:30%"/></p> <p>The Auto Cone project is an effort to develop cones that are capable of localizing and placing themselves to improve safety conditions for highway workers. These cones utilize RTK GPS and onboard localization filtering to produce decimeter-level accuracy in placing themselves in road conditions. Additionally, they are capable of transitioning through GPS-denied environments such as under bridges or overpasses. Pictured are two of the cones and the real-time kinematic (RTK) base station.</p> <h1 id="problem">Problem:</h1> <p><img src="/assets/img/Kinematics.png" alt="Kinematics" style="float:right;width:30%"/></p> <p>The goal of this project is to develop a robotic platform capable of automatically placing cones in a defined wedge shape behind the work vehicle within the starting lane. Specifically the cones shall:</p> <ul> <li>Place three cones in 40 foot increments in a wedge</li> <li>Begin the wedge 80 feet from the end of the vehicle</li> <li>Operate on highway surfaces unaffected by small debris</li> <li>Remain within the lane despite road curvature</li> <li>Not rely on magnetic or road-embedded sensors</li> <li>Have a speed greater than 0.3 m/s</li> <li>Cost less than $1,500 per cone unit</li> <li>Be easy to use and require little training</li> </ul> <h1 id="kinematics">Kinematics:</h1> <p>The omnidirectional platform makes the system holonomic, which means that with only three motors, the system can smoothly and directly move between any two states. This allows orientation to be independently controlled from position, and makes the system unconstrained by initial conditions. This is very advantageous for pick and place when deploying. The image outlines the kinematics used to drive the cone’s motion.</p> <h1 id="sensor-fusion">Sensor Fusion:</h1> <p><img src="/assets/img/RTK.png" alt="RTK GPS" style="float:right;width:30%"/></p> <p>Using a system of RTK GPS and a ground base station, the cone’s achieve a much lower position error than typical GPS for a relatively small increase in cost.</p> <p>Fusing these corrected GPS measurements with the higher rate encoders on the wheel motors provides the system with a high rate localization estimate that is robust in handling drift and sensor noise.</p> <h1 id="results">Results:</h1> <p>The results of this project were a functioning prototype system that is capable of deploying multiple cones without collision to a wedge shape formation while remaining within lane lines. The system is also capable of operating in GPS-denied environments.</p> <h1 id="videos">Videos</h1> <p>Deployment:</p> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0hgOc2csaWE" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> <p>The IV 2020 presentation slides are available <a href="/assets/pdf/2020-06-IV.pdf">here</a> and recording is available here:</p> <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cbcMwYcLUmk" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe> <h1 id="citation">Citation:</h1> <div class="language-bibtex highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nc">@inproceedings</span><span class="p">{</span><span class="nl">2020_AutoCone</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">author</span>    <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{Hartzer, Jacob and Saripalli, Srikanth}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">booktitle</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2020 IEEE Intelligent Vehicles Symposium (IV)}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">title</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{AutoCone: An OmniDirectional Robot for Lane-Level Cone Placement}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">year</span>      <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{2020}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">pages</span>     <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{1663-1668}</span><span class="p">,</span>
  <span class="na">doi</span>       <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s">{10.1109/IV47402.2020.9304683}</span><span class="p">,</span>
<span class="p">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Low-cost Navigation using Computer Vision</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2019/MEEN489/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Low-cost Navigation using Computer Vision"/><published>2019-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2019/MEEN489</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2019/MEEN489/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/HoughLine.png" alt="Hough Line" style="float:right;width:30%"/></p> <p>The North Texas Tollway Authority is an organization that runs and maintains toll roads and road infrastructure in the North Texas Area. They are responsible for collecting tolls and to use those tolls to fund projects and services connected to the infrastructure and use of these toll roads. This includes servicing the roadway itself, mobile repairs or service, and the monitoring of roads for safety and traffic conditions. This allows the NTTA to respond and adapt to changing conditions throughout the day and to better serve those who use their roads.</p> <p>Included in the monitoring of roads, the NTTA will freely respond to accidents or break- downs on the road. In addition to road work, this means NTTA needs to have the ability to access and safely cordon portions of the road to work or provide assistance to drivers.</p> <p>In order to achieve this need, NTTA has two attenuator trucks that are capable of withstanding a rear or side impact that are used to protect road workers while they are servicing the road or assisting drivers while not constricting access to the road itself. Additionally, there are numerous response trucks that are used in service but that also can also be used to block off a lane from the rear. Shown in Figure 1, the service truck in addition to the attenuator truck can be used to block off the entire shoulder and one lane while still allowing access to work within the lane.</p> <p>These attenuator trucks and service trucks are vital to the safety of the NTTA workers due to the unpredictability of drivers at all times of day. However, there have been issues with the number of vehicles that have collided with these trucks. Despite working as designed to protect the workers, the attenuator trucks have long downtimes after collision and a high cost to repair. At times, both trucks have been out of service, preventing the workers from being able to safely service the road or aid drivers. And while the response trucks can also be used to block traffic and protect workers, collisions with these trucks have the same issue of large costs for repairs.</p> <p>NTTA has found that placing cones in a wedge shape in front of the vehicles drastically reduces the number of collisions with the trucks by giving drivers additional warning that they are approaching road work. This is especially effective around corners and roads with high speed limits. The tradeoff is the placement of cones requires the workers to manually drop off and pick up the cones up to 120 feet away from the protection of the service and attenuator trucks. Due to the high risk of personal injury to workers, this was deemed unacceptable. Therefore, the NTTA desired a device that would be able to solve this problem. <a href="/assets/pdf/2019-05-MEEN-491H.pdf">Report</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Computer"/><category term="Vision,"/><category term="Experiments"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Multidisciplinary System Analysis Design Optimization</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2019/MEEN683/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multidisciplinary System Analysis Design Optimization"/><published>2019-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2019/MEEN683</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2019/MEEN683/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/Optimization.png" alt="Optimization" style="float:right;width:30%"/></p> <p>A triathlon is one of the few sports that depends on the quality and performance of a device to achieve optimal performance in a competition. The USA Triathlon Association (USAT) has registered more than 200,000 athletes with an annual membership (USAT, 2015), which represents around 35% of the total athletes present in the USAT events each year, this number keeps growing due to this sport is also taken as a personal challenge not just as a lifestyle.</p> <p>The number of athletes for one-day registration for competition in the USAT goes from 299,030 (USAT, 2015) until 371,988 (USAT, 2011), from 2010 through 2015 demographic registration. The cost for a triathlon bicycle could be from 2000 USD until 15000 USD, where the main differences are weight, frame shape, material, and aerodynamic properties that also have to be within the USAT rules.</p> <p>The triathlon bicycles that are currently in the market have an average weight of 8 kg (17.5 kg), where the frame represents an average of 1.36 kg (3 lb.) and the primary materials used for bicycle frames are AISI 1060 High Carbon Steel, ASTM A182 Chromoly Steel, Aluminum 6061-T4, Titanium, and Carbon Fiber.</p> <p>This article analyses the stresses, moments and torques present in an over-constrained frame system and optimizes the design of a customized bicycle frame for triathlon competition using Matlab optimization toolbox to obtain the optimal geometry configuration and material selection and SolidWorks to analyze the integrity of the frame based on the Matlab results. <a href="/assets/pdf/2019-05-MEEN-683.pdf">Final Report</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Design,"/><category term="Simulation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Advanced System Dynamics and Controls</title><link href="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2019/MEEN431/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advanced System Dynamics and Controls"/><published>2019-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2019/MEEN431</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhartzer.github.io//blog/2019/MEEN431/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/PIGA.png" alt="PIGA" style="float:right;width:30%"/></p> <p>A PIGA (Pendulous Integrating Gyroscopic Accelerometer) is a type of robust accelerometer that is about to measure both acceleration and change in velocity using dynamics of pendulous gyroscopes. This device was mainly used in rocket IMU systems, most famously the Saturn V. It has advantages over other accelerometers where, if a proper controller is used to stabilize the pendulum, the change in axial velocity is proportional to the rotation of the system, and therefore the acceleration is proportional to the angular rate. This reduces the drift and noise in the measurements.</p> <p>The goal of this project was to derive the equations of motion and the dynamics of the PIGA. Then we designed a controller to minimize steady state error based on the system. Additionally, motor dynamics were considered when shaping the controller gains. Finally, a controller was designed to track the Saturn V’s ascent profile without steady-state error. <a href="/assets/pdf/2019-05-MEEN-431.pdf">PIGA Analysis</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Controls,"/><category term="Simulation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>